A Guide to the Elaine G. Diacumakos papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA158
Rockefeller Archive Center
Elaine G. Diacumakos papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
1956-1984
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Diacumakos, Elaine G.
Rockefeller University
FA158
1.76 Cubic Feet 4 boxes. Extent is approximate.
4 document boxes.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 D54
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for scholarly research.
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Diacumakos, Elaine G.; Rockefeller University
- Biographical materials, 1
  - Curriculum vitae; bibliography to 1978, 5" Hollinger (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - ms. Elaine G. Diacumakos, "A procedure for determining the presence or absence of polynucleotide phosphorylase activity on the nucleolus". [Special written project for Ph. D examination. Submitted to the Commission in lieu of a written preliminary examination. M.J. Kopac, E.G. Diacumakos research advisor at NYU], 1956 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Elaine G. Diacumakos, "Microsurgical studies on the nuclei of Amoeba". Title of dissertation, 1958 June (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes copies of dissertation abstract, scientific photographs and legends for Figures 9-27.
  - Correspondence, [re] NIH fellowship and RI appointment as guest investigator in E.L. Tatum's laboratory, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with E.L. Tatum and other E.L. Tatum items, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - diary. As maintained by E.G. Diacumakos, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - calendars as maintained by E.G. Diacumakos, 1974 1975 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - RU Library Exhibit. "Micromanipulation of Living Cells from 1859", 1978 January-June (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Includes 2 photographs of E.G. Diacumakos taken when a graduate student at N.Y.U. and scientific photographs. Also includes 1 5x7 copy negative of Dr. Robert Chambers? (Used as part of exhibit); RU Calendar of Events 1978 Jan-June announcing exhibit; RU News and Notes, Jan 78, p. 4, article re exhibit.
  - Obituary material (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Includes.
    - Joshua Lederberg/RU Community, 1984 June 13
    - NEWS from The Rockefeller University, 1984 June 14
    - Newspaper clippings, 1985 June 14-15
    - RU News and Notes 13, 1984 June-July; 6 items
  - RU News and Notes article (re] 1974 Jan 27, WNBC-TV "Research Report" on E.G. Diacumakos techniques of microsurgery, 1974 February; 2½" (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes photocopy of text of article for RU News and Notes with E.G.D. corrections.
  - Frank Field - 6th hour news, 1974 March 15 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    [re] E.G. Diacumakos work.
    Includes various typescripts of Frank Field's report, one with corrections and New York Times, 1 May 1974, news clipping.
  - Contemporary Ob/Gyn, Vol 3, no 4, April 1974, pp 55-57. "Cell Surgery Points Way to Genetic Engineering". Article re E.G. Diacumakos' work on cell surgery, 1974 April (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Includes correspondence, edited and corrected copies of article, scientific photographs and 35mm negatives used in article and copy of April 1974 issue of Contemporary Ob/Gyn.
  - issues of Contemporary Ob/Gyn, 1973 December-1974 January (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - [re] Income Tax, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper, magazine clippings and 1980 Reprint, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - New York Times, "Injection of a Gene Cures Flaw in Cell", 1979 October 10
    - Chemical and Engineering News, "Genes Injected Into Deficient Cells", 1979 October
    - Boston Globe, "Hope for Genetic Disease Cure", 1979 October 14
    - Reprint. W. French Anderson, "Regulation of Globin Gene Expression at the Molecular Level". Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences 344 (1980) 262-279
  - Figures for book E.G. Diacumakos writing (Box 2, Folder 7)
    [As per M.W. Chase, 21 Sept 1984].
  - Miscellaneous Items (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Notes [re] computer programming - UNIX (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Photographs/negatives, some dated, some undated, 5" (Box 3)
    Includes scientific photographs and equipment; some of Elaine G. Diacumakos at microscope and with others; some of others and photographs of figures for 1973 Methods Paper by E.G.D. and some of travels?.
    - Scientific photographs and equipment (some in color) (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - 4 Kodachrome transparencies of E.G.D. at microscope, 1974 February
      - 1 5x7 print of E.G.D., Peter H. Sellers, and M.W. Chase, 11 June 1984 at RU Alumni Reunion, 1984 June 11
    - Photographs/negatives of equipment, 5 5 × 7 envelopes (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - 1 35mm negative of scientific equipment
      - 3 35mm negatives of microscope
      - Photos/35mm negatives in color of scientific equipment
      - Polaroid and other photos in color of scientific equipment
      - Transparencies of scientific equipment, 1980 April
        [Note in slide box by E.G.D. "Apr 18, 1980 Equipment" - all overexposed or out of focus - not one useful transparency].
    - Figures for 1973 Methods Paper (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Photos/negatives in color of travels, 1979 August, undated; 5 5 × 7 envelopes (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Polaroid shots taken in Philadelphia?
      - Photos/negs in color. Appear to be of travels - most taken from airplane, undated
      - Photos/negs in color of travels. Some of Kitt Peak, National Observatory Center, Arizona?, undated
      - Photos/negs in color of travels. Most taken from airplane, 1979 August
      - Transparencies of travels. In a box, 1979 August
    - Photographs of others (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Auclaire, Walter, 2 polaroid prints of...
      - Berrios, Miquel, 2 black and white prints of...
      - Bertolotti, Roger - 2 polaroid prints; 1 with inscription
      - Unidentified, 1 polaroid print
  - Memorabilia, In a legal size 5" Hollinger box (Box 4)
    - Diagram. Paris Conference (1971) Fig 5 (Box 4)
    - Diagrammatic representation of chromosome bands as observed with the Q-, G-, and R-staining methods; centromere representative of Q-staining method only. p. 19 (Box 4)
    - Photocopy (Box 4)
      [Original given to Mr. Lyons for Mr. Chimonides 21 Dec 1984 by Carolyn Kopp].
    - Inscription: "To Elaine - On the eve of your prelims all the luck to a gal who certainly deserves it. Signed "Oliver". On title page of ms by A.S. Gordon, S.J. Piliero, P.T. Medici, CD. Siegel, and M. Tannenbaum, "Attempts to Identify Site of Production of Circulating 'Erythropoietin'". Proceedings of the Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine 92 (1956) 598-602 (Box 4)
    - Reprint request for Diacumakos ms in PNAS 69 (10): 2959; 1972. from Barid B. Mukherjee, Prof, of Genetics. McGill University (Box 4)
    - Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center. Telephone Directory, 1965-1966 (Box 4)
    - The Rockefeller University Telephone Book, 1976-1977 (Box 4)
    - Handwritten list of names (Box 4)
    - Frisbee, Tennis Ball, Xylonite Triangle (Box 4)
    - 1984 Calendar, Au-Brion Press (Box 4)
    - Colored illustration (print) of E.L. Tatum, from Scientific Products (Box 4)
    - Chart of metabolic pathways, 1977. Designed by D.E. Nicholson. Published by Koch-Light, Colebrook, England (Box 4)